software engineering radio episode 60
scrum
welcome to another episode of the
software engineering radio today we talk
about scrum with almond peeler which is
another episode in our Assaf 28th adachi
serious so woman could you please
introduce yourself a bit
my name is some woman pitler I work as
an independent scrum consultant and
scrum trainer in the UK and I'm
currently helping large American
financial institution to
institutionalize and embrace scrum okay
so what scrum scrum is an agile
framework focused on management
practices project management and
requirements management practices okay
where did it come from or who invented
it scrum was invented by Jeff Sutherland
and Ken Schreiber in the early 1990s it
is inspired by Lean Thinking it is also
inspired by the Theory of Constraints
which is another management approach
evolutionary processes processes that
evolve rather than being prescribed in a
prescriptive way iterative incremental
software development certainly which was
some popular you know throughout the 90s
and engineering tools from the small
talk engineering and community and an
important inspiration for for scrum was
ignored tickle published in 1986 in the
Harvard Business Review by two Japanese
gentleman called Takeuchi and Nonaka and
that article was called the new product
development game and investigated how
Japanese companies managed to
significantly reduce time to market of
new product development efforts while at
the same time increasing product quality
and customer satisfaction and as I said
before lean and Lean Thinking and
Japanese approaches to
product development by an important
source and inspiration for scrum and
actually scrum and lean fit very very
nicely together yeah interesting to see
how all these methodologies based on the
same roots so what are the basic ideas
in principle behind scrum well I'd say a
key idea a key principle of scrum is to
have an empower to autonomous self
organizing team that delivers business
value and in on a regular basis in a in
a repeat unit in a reliable way
typically within every one to four weeks
and in a software development context
scrum stipulates that the business value
has to have the form of a potentially
shippable product increment so a piece
of software that's tested and adequately
documented and typically implements some
some requirements and has to sort of be
available at the end of an Intel at the
end of the iteration at the end of a
sprint okay okay may ask what's a team
in scrum well scrum talk I mean we
talked already about extreme programming
where team is pretty defined is the same
true in scrum well in scrum a team is a
fairly small and dedicated team so a
scrum team typically has seven plus
minus two team members it has to be an
empowered team that has the authority to
make decisions has the right to select
its own iteration goal guided by the
product owner and that's another role in
scrum so it's a small team a dedicated
team it's empowered it is
self-organizing so a scrum team should
be able to organize it's a homework and
the way people collaborate and it also
needs to be autonomous it needs to be
able to deliver work and more or less
independent of the rest of the
organization of other teams and a scrum
team is also collectively responsible
for delivering an iteration goal and
making a commitment and sticking to it
executing on that commitment
so the team is really the basis not when
we later talk about scrum of scrums
that's not the team anymore it's really
the basic team here even large scrum
projects are made of multiple teams so
the way to scale the scrum is or scrum
Portugese rather than to increase the
size of a team new teams are added and
those new teams also need to be
dedicated which means team members work
typically full-time on the team and have
to sort of have to follow the attributes
you know exhibit the attributes we just
discussed in the same way as a single
scrum team or some single scrum team
project has to there's there's another
thing that's I'd like I'd like to
mention and that is scrum teams should
be co-located to facilitate close
collaboration and close communication of
the team members okay
so let's switch over to the practices I
would suggest what are the basic scrum
practices what scrum one scrum well
scrum provides management practices
requirements management and project
management practices and the
requirements management practices are
pretty much focused around dealing with
what we call in scrum the product
backlog which is a list of requirements
a list of prioritized requirements and
the management practices are centered
around release management managing the
entire project managing creating a
project plan which we call the release
plan in scrum estimating and tracking
the project but also managing sprints
and a sprint is simply the word for
iteration in scrum the managing sprints
means planning sprints estimating tasks
tracking tasks daily stand-up meetings
which we call daily scrums in scrum and
at the end of an often offer Springs we
have a review and a retrospective in
scrum so
scrum is is in a way very simple in the
sense that it off
a small set of rules you could say or
you know recommendations and the idea
behind having a small set of clear rules
is that you know picking the right rules
will generate meaningful and intelligent
behavior so that goes back to one of the
sources of scrum evolutionary and
complex adaptive systems okay
so let's jump into this Prince thing as
you said Sprint's are the iterations in
scrum so they are the the driving factor
I guess can you talk a bit about sprints
yes Sprint's spent in scrum is a mini
project basically so it is synonymous
for iteration a sprint she should have a
goal so it should be clear to all the
stakeholders what the objective of the
Sprint is what's team and product owner
are trying to achieve and get out of the
sprints and Bennett sprints typically
starts always starts with a sprint
planning meeting so the product owner
and the team get together
the product owner introduces the Sprint
goal to the team and the requirements
that make up the Sprint goal for
instance you know if this was the first
Sprint's of the project the product
owner could choose something like tall
trees have strong roots for instance as
as as a sprint goal and in select
adequate and requirements that fulfill
that goal and then the team would go
through the list of requirements we'll
discuss each requirement with the
product owner identify tasks estimate
the tasks and then you know look at the
team's availability look at the team's
knowledge and skills distribution and
then say okay um as a team can we
collectively commit to that requirements
or currently and once all the
requirements have been discussed all the
Obey availability and you know the
knowledge within the team's been
consumed that spring planning is
basically done and then the team makes a
final commitment and says okay this is
what we're going for this is a
commitment this is a promise this is
what we're going to deliver within the
sprints
and that's the end of the Sprint
planning session so I'd rather than
other agile approaches like extreme
programming sprint planning in scrum is
a commitment based or commitment driven
planning approach approach where the
entire team makes a collective
commitment and in promise mm-hmm
in order for that to work scrum requires
that Sprint's are protected from any
changes so even though in scrum we do
welcome change and we embrace change
what we say is for the duration of one
to four weeks depending on the sprint
length we basically freeze time and
functionality requirements and also
quality I mean in scrum we always want
to deliver software with high quality
but we don't typically allow any changes
once the Sprint couple has been
committed by the team what happens if
the girls aren't reached in one sprint
what happens with the these features or
however they called what happens if a
team can't deliver yeah all the features
it promised any committed well you know
basically from from from the teams and
the product owners perspective the
Sprint wasn't wasn't successful at least
entirely success but it sort of depends
how how many requirements our team
didn't managed to deliver in to a
certain extent why that happened
sometimes team members for Leland and
that's difficult to talk to to
accommodate for but essentially the
approach that scrum recommends is to put
all those features or all those
requirements that weren't delivered back
into the product backlog and therefore
those features have to be reworked or we
redeliver or worked on again in one of
the subsequent sprints so in scrum
harshly done work is never taken into
account only work that's fully done and
is accepted by the product owner at the
end of the Sprint and only that work is
is earned in a way and you know if you
work with an estimating techniques such
as story points only only part when you
fully done work would earn a team story
points in
sort of then make up the team's velocity
so the planning for Sprint is well it
has to be reasonable you have to plan
some buffering and holidays or whatever
comes in this four week iteration just
the big hours have to be reachable yes
the girls have to be realistic and it's
sort of you know scrum ultimately is all
about collaboration particularly between
the product owner and the team so it's
up to the product owner to get a feel
for the team's capacity and capability
and formulates a realistic Sprint goal
and select pre-selected or shortlist in
adequate adequate user stories adequate
requirements and it's up to the team to
ensure that it acknowledged develop
availability in those it's it's smallish
distribution prior to the planning
meeting and typically you know that's
something that you know the team and the
product owner at least you know a good
product I named a team that's used to
the process we'll talk about prior to
the planning meeting upfront and I have
a quick chat about you know the upcoming
user stories and so that the product
owner gets some feedback and the team
gets some visibility of what's coming
what's coming along but because the
whole thing is a commitment driven
planning approach as you rightly said it
is important that the team is clear and
what it's actually able to do because
ultimately the team does doesn't make a
promise in scrum and it is bad practice
to to break a promise and input
undermine eventually the trust between
the product owner and the team of the
team and I did continue to to fail
meeting its its commitments and spring
commitments okay anything more to Adams
on Sprint's oh yeah on a daily basis
within the Sprint we have what's called
a daily scrum which is a meeting that's
has to two objectives it helps the team
to synchronize and understand what
everybody is up to basically and also
typically you know reflect briefly on
the project progress and it also helps
to identify in a systematic way any
impediments blockages any issues that
help that prevent the team from being as
productive as it could be
and an Escalade and highlight highlight
those impediments so that's that's the
daily scrum and that's a short time
boxed meeting by the way all meetings in
trauma time most the daily scrum is
typically 15 minutes it takes place at
the same same same same location same
place and same same same time every day
so it's very similar to a stand-up in
extreme programming that's a daily
meeting and at the end of the Sprint we
have two more meetings a refew meeting
in a retrospective meeting and the
review meeting is there so that the team
can demo all the work results to the
product owner the product owner can
inspect the software system that's
that's evolved in this sprint typically
in inform of you know seeing tests upon
the rule so you not being having the
opportunity to execute tests him or
herself playing around with the software
having a browse through the
documentation making sure that all the
conditions of satisfaction of the
requirements the user stories are
actually fulfilled so that's the review
meeting and and ultimately the review
meeting determines how much progress
that he made and if the team managed to
meet its commitments or if the team
under-delivered or sometimes you know
even even either delivered we have the
retrospective which is also mandatory
time boxed meeting and scrum and it's
there for the team to understand how the
team's been working together how the
team's applied the process and what the
team could possibly do in order to
improve the way the team that must work
together okay
the product owner in which meetings is
he is seeing the daily scrum - I
typically recommend that the product
owner does attend the daily scrum I
think it's good practice to have a
product owner net and works closely with
the team now the product owner is really
responsible for specifying the
requirements defining what's value-added
from from an end customer perspective is
so the product owner in a ways is the
voice of the customer is a customer and
customer representative sometimes you
know maybe even be a good idea to ask
and use an end customer to take on the
role of a product owner in larger
organizations the programmer typically
comes from marketing and product
management but should be in close
contact with and real end-users and
really understand the end user the end
customers needs and then perspective and
it is good practice that the product
owner closely collaborate with the team
throughout the sprints hmm that helps
the product owner to understand that the
progress made by the team and you know
it helps to right-size the the upcoming
user stories and requirements for the
next sprint okay so he doesn't have to
know about software development
processes at all he just has to have
domain knowledge well the part owner
certainly has to have the main knowledge
has to be able to look at the software
from an end customers and users
perspective I think the ideal product I
own also knows about how software's
actually developed it doesn't
necessarily mean that the product owner
has you know deep deep programming
skills but it would be good that you
know the product owner has at least a
rough idea how software is developed why
it is necessary for instance to employ
certain development practices or you
know what good and what bad development
practices are that just helps the
product owner to make the right
decisions
if you scrum is is quite interesting
when you look at how the roles interact
then you have the team which is quite a
quite a strong role really one of the
cool roles as this autonomous
self-organizing empowers and entity and
then you have the product owner which is
which is the second strong role in scrum
and the prod owner guides and in a way
also you know directs the team and
putting forwards and requirements that
are consumed by the team and turned into
working software and helping you know
having the knowledge at least a rough
understanding of house of the
development works will it will help the
product owner is sort of to make make
sure that the whole process is is smooth
and flows nicely but interesting to see
that the product owner isn't part of the
team
which is some other methodologies see
them as part of the team here oh yeah I
guess you scrum you know Matt my answer
will be I'd leave that up to a certain
extent to to the team in the product
owner and the organization to be honest
I think that the product owner should
work closely with the team and product
owners are typically classed as chickens
in scrum when it comes down to the daily
scrum so they're allowed to talk at the
daily scrum could you get I'm not sure
everybody knows this chicken pic thing
explain please
we've got two types of animals in scrum
pigs and chicken pigs are those project
members and stakeholders that are
encouraged to talk at the daily scrum
and chickens are people that are
stakeholders more remote stakeholders
that have an interest in the outcome of
the project but really don't contribute
on a daily basis and have met a many
commitment in terms of the Sprint goal
and those those chickens are typically
not not encouraged or they're not even
allowed to talk at the daily scrum so
product owners are typically cast as as
pigs when it comes down to the daily
scrum and you know sometimes product
owners take on tasks within the sprints
such as performing acceptance level
testing but that sort of depends on the
product owner it also depends a little
bit on the team independent of how
independent of if the prior owner takes
on tasks related to the Sprint goal I
would recommend that the better product
owner works with the team on a daily
basis has time to answer questions of
the team has time to understand that the
progress certainly attends to daily
scrum but you know it's maybe also able
to execute some acceptance tests simply
as I said to be clear on you know I have
how far has the team gotten to avoid any
any surprises at the end of the Sprint
the projects the scrum projects and
teams I've worked with you know those
that had engaged product owners that
worked closely with the team and had the
opportunity to spend quite a bit of time
you know together with the team you know
I sort of been sort of you know
partially co-located or at least you
know
taking along the laptop and working in
our a couple of hours a day aside with
the team alongside the team those teams
and projects did really well teams where
the product owner was hardly available
and you know just child up for the for
the for the spring planning and then
maybe occasionally for daily scrum and
Bend then for the sprint review session
those teams had more the tendency to
struggle and find finally difficult very
even for the product owner it doesn't
necessarily have to be you know of
proper team member in scrum close
collaboration is necessary okay as we
talked about or we already finished the
role product owner so maybe we should
continue with the other rows you already
mentioned the team what's the team the
team is a small dedicated team in scrum
so the scrum team consists of seven plus
minus two team members team members
typically work full-time on the on the
project on the scrum team and team
members are typically co-located now
what's important about a scrum team is
that it needs to be an empowered team
and that means the team members have the
right to make a commitment in the sprint
planning meeting and commit to an
iteration goal and select the user
stories that the team feels it can
actually realistically commit to it
needs to be autonomous that means it
needs to be able to deliver the spring
commitments in independent independence
of other teams and projects it also
needs to be self-organizing and that
means it needs to be able to organize
itself and its work on on a daily basis
without needing anyone to direct the
team you know and then manage the team
so that's that's that's a that's a scrum
team and typically a scrum team is also
cross-functional which means it contains
functions roles from different parts of
the organization another way to look at
this is to say everybody who needs to
contribute to creating and delivering a
software system and should also be part
of the scrum team sorry
typically programmers and architects are
part of the scrum team but also test us
also people invite the documentation
maybe user interface designer sometimes
it may even make sense to have somebody
from marketing or business analyst as
part of a scrum team okay but how does
this work I mean if I hear I have an
test an architect and software developer
and UI designer and the documentation
guy whatever these were already five
roads if I have teams just up to seven
plus or minus a few people the the teams
are pretty small actually I can't do
much in a scrum team no in a way that's
a balancing act but but typically when
you look at how many functions are
involved in developing a piece of
software then you know there aren't that
many more than I just listed mmm and
sometimes it may make sense to form
dedicated teams for instance you know
you could you could have sort of an
exploration phase or investigation phase
where you do where you investigate the
user interface design and you may do
some upfront UI design and then you know
limits the the genuine new UI this
amount of new UI design that's done
within the Sprint's but you know that's
sort of up to a specific project really
to see how you can really optimize value
creation but but typically the teams are
fought with consisted of as I said you
know programmers architects testers DBAs
somebody that's able to write
documentation particularly when you need
end user and customer documentation and
that's typically quite a quite a
powerful scrum team okay okay so last
role I know office the scrum master you
already mentioned you are one so what
what's a scrum master what does what's
this job in the project the scrum master
well I'd say the scrum master is
responsible for teaching the scrum
process ends being a role model as they
cited to walk the talk basically and
that implies challenging conventional
habits and in thinking and at the same
time to encourage new thinking in new
of working that are compliant with agile
and scrum so it's a certain extent the
scrum master is a change agent and
that's typically the case when scrum is
first introduced in in an organization
the scrum master is also responsible for
looking after the team health the scrum
master helps the team to gel and become
a performing team a true team and scrum
must also shields the team from external
interferences we've already discussed
we've already mentioned that Sprint's
are protected from any changes now it's
the job of the scrum master for instance
to make sure that that actually happens
and in that sense act a little bit as
you know ken Shriver says as a sheepdog
and you're not barking sometimes maybe
even bites if any intruders come and try
to do things like and steal people off
off the scrum team or you know change
the Sprint goal midway through mm-hmm
the scrum master also tries to enable
the product owner so we drive in stair
developments directly by removing any
barriers between the product owner ends
the team and now in conventional
software development we typically have a
number of barriers between a product
owner in the team I mean we have a
project manager we have typically
analysts or architects sometimes
designers and the idea in scrum base
they'd be saying well we do we do away
with all those barriers and all that
sort of floated hierarchy we have all
the performers all the right people on
the team so we've got a capable team and
then that product owner should be able
to work directly with the team and if
the scrum master is really there to
facilitate that relationship so the
scrum master is not a project manager
certainly not in the traditional sense
the scrum master is much more like like
a leader and a facilitator mm-hmm and
finally that the scrum master also has
to help the organization to to deal with
any impediments and in problems and in
issues that the surface when scrum is
first applied and things like the
configuration management environment is
not capable and up to scratch it needs
to be replaced and you saw there needs
to be you needs to be in
installed or maybe new memory needs to
be bored I mean fairly trivial things
like that that sometimes still you know
have have an impact in terms of you know
raising some budget or bigger issues
like the product owner the product
owners availability is too restricted he
or she needs to spend be able to spend
more time with the team to do a really
good job those are things that scrum
master has to has to sort of help to
resolve and and if necessary escalate
through the organization and being being
a scrum master is sort of an awkward
thing because if you're good scrum
master you tried to work yourself out of
a job as quickly as possible which means
that over time the team learns to be a
self-organizing team the team has has
learned to employ the process
effectively and the organization has
learned to you fully leverage scrum and
and reap all of scrums benefits and at
that point in time and the scrum master
role per se doesn't become redundant but
being a scrum master is no longer a
full-time job it's probably more a
part-time job and you know scrum masters
can then move on and be also performance
on the team that's typically difficult
right at the beginning when you first
start when you start your first scrum
team early on scrum being a scrum master
typically means you know the scrum
master job is typically a full-time job
and I'm guessing we're through with the
Rose laundry yeah I saw that those are
the three absolutely right those are the
three roles in scrum not anymore
all we have is product on a team and in
scrum master and in a way product iron
and team make it take in the scrum
masters get to facilitate and lead and
particularly you know help with
establishing scrum teaching the process
and those all the roles we have in scrum
okay in the introduction on the question
what is scrum you mentioned the product
backlog which is a central point and
scrum to me can you give us a few words
on this the product backlog is essential
requirements management tool in scrum it
is a list of requirements and those
requirements have to be Pro
heist in scrum their prior prioritized
by valued benefit by risk and by cost so
the primary that dimensions for
prioritization are a really value in
risk and it's the job of the product
owner to pull together an initial
product backlog stock it with
requirements and do a first
prioritization the the product backlog
feeds the scrum team so in preparation
for each sprint planning meeting the
product owner selects short lists the
high priority requirements from the
product backlog and puts it forwards to
the team and those requirements that I
have been then are successfully
transformed into potentially shippable
product increment are then taken out of
the product backlog and as a product
owner if I want to add new requirements
and to the project I just added to the
product backlog I can amend requirements
in the product backlog at any time I can
change the priority but it typically
doesn't have any impact on the team
until the next sprint planning meeting
takes place the prioritization how does
it work I mean in my experience we often
end up with priority lists where 90% of
the features are priority a and
everything else is B or C which doesn't
help so much and it's even worse I guess
if you have three dimensions like
business values market and technical
risk I mean which is the order we we
work out the features afterwards yeah I
mean ultimately in scrum it is really
the job of the product owner to get the
privatization right that doesn't mean
that the team doesn't doesn't contribute
and help in scrum week we say that most
of the features and functionality that
are typically delivered by software
systems are rarely or never used that
goes back to I think the chaos report of
the Standish Group in I think 2003 or so
I tried that you know up to 60 65
percent of all features on software
systems are typically really are never
used so one of the things we tell
product owners is if you want to
optimize value creation and if you want
to cut out waste then why don't you
really focus on those features that help
to make a difference for your end users
and customers are critical to the task
end users try to perform or you know a
critical in order to sell a software
product to end customers figuring out
which of those features are the most
important ones is then ultimately the
job of the product owner and they're in
a number of ways you can do it what want
one of the tricks a good thing typically
to do is to a group requirements by
themes now if you use user stories as
you describe the requirements
description technique then a theme is
simply a cohesive set of user stories
and you first prioritize the product
backlog by themes before you try to
prioritize on a user story level the
reason for that is when user stories
tend to be very fine-grained
requirements and often it's very
difficult to associate a business value
with a very fine-grained detailed
requirement even if that requirements
still represents an end and use our end
customers perspective so in order to
prioritize from a from a from a from a
financial or from a from a from a value
and benefits a perspective grouping by
themes and prioritizing by themes is a
good strategy but it comes down to risk
it is certainly a good idea to talk to
the team and see which technical risks
the team perceives and which
requirements exhibits a great deal of
technical risks and should be addressed
early on in the project to make sure
that the team has the right approach to
deal and handle with those to deal with
those requirements and implement them
adequately and successfully mm-hmm how
do technical features come in I mean
something like basic frameworks or
database access layers or stuff like
this has to be the or even a build
machine has to be done by the team
someone in the project how does this be
how does it get into the requirement
list or does it at all I mean maybe not
I typically recommend that anything the
product owner ultimately has to pay for
should should make its way into the
product backlog and should appear in the
product backlog so if the team has to
set up its development environment and
install a new build machine and
configure that build machine I would say
that should be a line item in the
product backlog mm-hmm if you really
want to go down to the to the level of
technical requirements and say well we
should use a vector base access layer
you know that's a slightly different
question I would say generally no I
would I would keep the product backlog
it's I would I would keep the
requirements in the product backlog at
an end-user in customer level and not
really go down to specific solutions I
think architecture models are a better
way to capture design decisions and and
make informed design decisions than the
product backlog so I'd really sort of
separate the concerns you know design
decisions technical decisions and and
end user requirements that's that's my
general recommendation I mean if you if
you if you if you are in a situation
where you have multiple teams and
feeding off the same product backlog and
those teams are organized along
subsystem boundaries and are component
or architecture teams then it could
possibly make sense to split out
end-user requirements into more
technical ones but you know that'd be
that'd be sort of the less preferred
option from my perspective I very much
when it comes to comes down to scaling
up scrum very much favors feature teams
over component architecture teams and
again that allows you then to keep your
product backlog nice and clean and tidy
and slight requirements from an end-user
perspective and leave it up to the team
to decide how they gonna get implemented
ok so it's ok for you if there are some
sprints where just where if you user
requirements are actually implemented
because parts of the team do these
technical stuff and the product owner
doesn't see it in his list yes that can
happen it can happen that the first one
or two sprints
don't creates much
in terms of business value I mean the
general requirements scrum places on
Sprint says that every sprint must
create potentially shippable product
increment and provide some business
value
now that increment in the very first
sprint could be very very small it could
be you know very potentially shippable
but it would be a good idea to to create
something that that sort of shows that
the team is able to make progress and
gives the team confidence gives the
product owner confidence and shows that
things are moving in the right direction
even in the first sprint if the team
can't do that then really the team isn't
in a position to start the first proper
sprint the team then needs to do some
upfront investigation or exploration
work which is in a way sort of a little
bit similar to what you have in XP and
extreme programming where you have an
exploration phase menus and pre work so
sometimes that's also the case that
simply the team needs to do a couple of
Sprint's of pre work but I wouldn't then
say that those are proper Sprint's
because the team wouldn't be in a
position to create potentially shippable
product increment okay and how you
approach how you approach it how you
play it is really up to the product
owner and the team it comes down to what
we call release planning in scrum and
release planning consists of two parts
one is estimating and the other one is
planning so once the product backlog has
been stocked once an initial product
backlog has been created and the team in
the product owner would get together and
the team would estimate each line item
in the product backlog and that would
also give the pro owner and a very rough
idea in terms of sort of you know
associated effort that is required in
order to deliver a specific product
backlog item and the second thing is the
team wants then estimate or hopefully
maybe even lower at this you know
depending on when you perform has been
planning and the team what sort of work
out its velocity and then say you know
given debía employ for instance to beat
sprints and we have the following
velocity and this is the amount of
efforts say story points in the
and back lock this is how long it's
going to take of us so what we typically
recommend in scrum is that early on in
the scrum project a release plan a
project plan is created that states the
likely order of delivery of specific
requirements of the requirements holding
the product backlog simply to align the
expectations of the product owner and
the other stakeholders I mean as a
product owner I need to know when all
the their must-haves the man the
mandatory the high the high priority
requirements of my software system can
be shipped so you know I can make
meaningful decisions in terms of you
know time feature set and cost budget
okay so let's say we finished our sprint
and now we have to do the sprint review
meeting your or and they already
mentioned the sprint review meeting in
scrum well unlike any meeting in scrum
sprint review meeting is time boxed and
the length depends on the smaller sprint
length and the longer the sprints the
more time you have to spend in the
review meeting
now the refew meeting is really an
opportunity for the product owner to
understand the project progress get
together with the team and have a look
at inspect the software created by the
team it's an opportunity for the team to
take pride in what the team's achieved
and accomplished and demo it to the
product owner and get feedback from the
product owner so at the end as part of
the review meeting we really want to
understand what the real project
progress is and the approach of the
agenda of the review meeting is very
simple and the team goes through the
list of committed requirements and demos
the requirements to the product owner
and that should be a live demo and that
means an official builds is is deployed
on a target machine and tests executed
in real time in front of the product
owner in the product owner should also
have the opportunity to execute tests or
play around with the software to
understand if the requirements were
adequately implemented or not mm-hmm and
the prone owner may also want to look
through other artifacts such as
documentation any
any any artifacts that are you to put
the work agreements between the product
owner and the team and they need to be
creative things like Javadoc for
instance or UML documentation or user
documentation and just sort of to make
sure that the documentation is there and
that he's happy with the quality because
ultimately the product owner is
responsible for the return of investment
is responsible for making sure that
money is spent wisely and the product
outcome or the project outcome is the
satisfy the end user needs so that's why
we have the demo meeting the ref your
meeting so the product owner can can get
feedback on with regards to the work
results delivered and can understand the
progress made so the important thing
about understanding the project progress
in the sprint reflow meeting is that the
product owner should only accept what
results that are done and work results
are done in scrum when the conditions of
satisfaction for each requirement is
adequately implemented by the team
that's why it's so important to carry
out tests as part of the review meeting
and have a live demo okay so the scrum
see I mean it's this just a demo after a
sprint or are these really releases
where the customer gets it software or
even it's getting sold or whatever this
releases or others just demo points yeah
good question
well as we discussed a few times scrum
requires that the outcome of each
sprints and must create some business
value and must be a potentially
shippable product increment so whatever
comes out of a sprint should be able to
be shipped to an end customer or end
user it's up to the product owner to
decide if the product owner wants to
actually release it and put it into
production so say for instance you have
a scrum project that lasts six months
the Prada owner could decide that he'll
release after three months and then
again release after six months at the
end of the project all the product owner
could decide that he releases software
at the end of each
it's entirely up to the product owner
and product owner and team should agree
prior to like the early at the beginning
of the project how long it will take the
team to transform a potentially
shippable product increment into a truly
shippable product increment say for
instance you provide an IT solution then
often the organization's procedures
around putting something into production
determine how long and how quickly you
can actually shift something you know
you may have to go into some sort of
steering board meeting or review meeting
to be allowed to put something into
production or the organization may say
well we can we only put new software
systems into production once a month or
something so you know there may be
external constraints that may determine
how often the team can then actually put
something in production and ship it okay
the other meat or the other review
meeting big review meeting is the
retrospective meeting after yeah after
the project as I understood you how is
this conducted what's happening in there
yeah the retrospective is another very
important and mandatory meeting in scrum
actually it's part of every sprint so
it's not only every performed at the end
of the project but actually at the end
of each sprint it's an opportunity for
the team to reflect on how the team's
been how the team has been working so I
find and you know how well the team
managed to collaborate in in in the last
sprint so it's all about saying you know
what went well and particularly what
didn't go so well to identify the key
issues the team is facing and I'm
focused on the key issue perform a root
cause analysis and come up with
actionable improvement measures that can
be then put forwards to the next sprint
planning meeting and the retrospective
really is there to help the team you
could say improve the process improve
the way the team collaborates works
together and make make work ultimately
more fun okay
the important thing may be about the
retrospective to be in mind is that you
know in order to make it at respective
what can have an if
activate perspective it is important to
facilitate it well it is important to
prepare it well you know I have the
right setting and set the stage properly
and do some timekeeping have a structure
think about and techniques and tools as
a facilitator you can suggest to the
team to extract issues and problems for
instance you know to use index cards as
a structure brainstorming technique so
those are things that are important to
to be in mind and typically you know it
is to be it is probably a good idea for
the scrum master to facilitate the first
few vet respectives to sort of lead the
teams through the process and also to
ensure that there's no blaming you know
any issues that come up you should be
part of you know you could say the
general work habits and how things are
done in the organization rather than an
individual's fault that's something as a
facilitator and scrum master you want to
watch out for that you know the
retrospective doesn't turn into a
blaming game and I think it's also
important to focus the team on what the
team can actually do to improve its way
of working
sometimes the team is heavily
constrained by external factors and
needs and some management supports and
some support by um organization and
that's good to know to notice but you
know sometimes it can be a danger of
finger pointing too much at people
outside of the team rather than sort of
sitting down and reflecting on how as a
team how can we improve the way we work
together the way we collaborate the way
we make decisions for instance the way
we deal with issues and conflicts you
know how how well did the daily scrum
work how come that you know we had
difficulties and time boxing it how come
then you know people didn't arrive on
time how come that the last planning
meeting was a pain and was very
difficult yeah those are sort of things
you want to discuss in their
retrospective okay I guess we are
through with the overview of scrum and
could answer or I could give a few
frequently asked questions to you
regarding some but before this are we
have everything covered you you want to
talk about
in the overview I think we've covered
sort of the core of off scrum at least
briefly it may be worth talking about
issues that are likely are frequently
issues that frequently arise when you
when you first when you start your first
scrum project but maybe that's that's
part of your frequently asked questions
why don't we but why don't we see what
the questions are and then we take
things from there okay one thing that
comes to mind for me always if I talk
about scrum a lot of people think scrum
is a software development methodology as
XP is to me personally I don't think
it's a software development methodology
it's more approaching management
framework or however I should call it
now there aren't a lot of parts of how
do I do coding how do I write
requirements down there do you have the
same a few on this or am I getting
things wrong there yeah that's a scrum
is a national framework for developing
software systems it people certainly
designs with the intention in mind to
use to use it as a framework for
software development you're absolutely
right it does not contain any specific
recommendations for development
practices it is really focused on
management project management practices
and requirements management practices
however scrum does stipulate that each
that the outcome of each sprint must be
potentially shippable and if a team
wants to create potentially shippable
product increment in a reliable way
then the team does have to reflect on
how it actually creates the software how
it tests the software and most scrum
teams I've worked with ended up
embracing scrum sorry embracing extreme
programming development practices and
just test first and refactoring and
continuous integration so you can think
of scrum like like you know I wrap up
with a framework where you can drop in
specific practices you need such as
extreme programming development
practices actually be my next question
what's the relationship between
extreme programming and special and the
HR movement in general and scrum as I
think they they fit well together at
least extreme programming and scrum as
you said yeah I think so I think it's XP
and scrum go together real nice and I've
worked with quite a few teams that
embraced you know scrum and incorporate
its extreme programming development
practices there's there's also a fair
overlap when it comes down to project
management and requirements management
practices
I think scrum and XP are really sort of
like a grind together in a way and you
can see that from the fact that in scrum
now we we teach you know user stories or
you know and we have a certain you know
many many scrum teams have started to
easy to employ user stories as a
requirements description technique we've
started to teach velocity and story
points as estimation and tracking
techniques which originate from extreme
programming so I think the two things
are growing together and they fit very
nicely that's that's my experience okay
same here one question I often get asked
is who uses blah blah blah extreme
programming scrum whatever because a lot
of people think they are pretty new and
scrum isn't that new nevertheless are
there any references you can give us I
think the list of scrum companies that
employ scrum this is growing and growing
and maybe just a few Yahoo uses scrum
Microsoft s ap British Telecom BBC Nokia
Motorolla
Siemens and many others particularly in
the last few years we've seen some major
companies embrace scrum and certainly
experimented with scrum and execute
individual scrum projects and I think
it's simply down to the fact that even
larger organizations now understand that
scrum can give them a significant
significant competitive advantage in
terms
you know shortening time to market
increasing product quality being more
flexible increasing productivity and you
know companies are looking into reaping
those those benefits scrums seems to
have a certain appeal to to larger
companies at least in my opinion I mean
there are not so many huge companies
using extreme programming or lean
software development the future driven
development but a scrum has on very
impressive user list on the largest
company side do you have any idea why
this is I don't know why to be honest it
may be may be simply because scrum is
called scrum or not extreme programming
or extreme something I'm not sure really
I mean maybe maybe to a certain
explenation or maybe a potential
explanation could be that scrum is more
focused on management practices and that
that makes it you know in quotation
marks in an easiest sell to you know
c-level management like a CEO or CIO CTO
it's not so sure you know it'll be
interesting to see how that tremendous
and how many large organizations really
embrace fully embrace scrum over an
extended period of time so how should I
start if I want to use scrum the most
important question I guess here how I
should you start how should you start to
use scrum well I guess I guess part of
setting yourself up for success is
finding a good pilot project and I'd say
it's probably a good idea to find a
scrum pilots a project to try out an
experiment with scrum that does have
some business relevance so does
something that's meaningful to the
business and where the business has has
a real interesting or the end users have
a real interest in that but at the same
time is not mission critical so you know
a project where you actually have the
opportunity to make a mistake and
recover from a mistake because like
anything new that you try out the first
time and there is a learning curve
you'll have to go through and as human
beings we typically only learn by making
mistakes so you know a certain mistake
tolerance within the project is probably
a good idea
so that's that's my first piece of
advice I have in terms of how you
approach it well the traditional my way
to get scrum going in an organization is
simply to do it try it out find the
product owner find somebody from from
the business or the end user community
that's well in fact there's a product
owner pulled together cross-functional
team that has the right people the right
performance in it and is as autonomous
as possible and you know get going you
know I start with the first pull
together an initial product backlog and
then start with the first sprint and
take things from there really
so that's that's the traditional way to
do experiments scrum mints and scrum
going in an organization and in the last
few years an alternative approach has
become popular and that is really you
know to make scrum a strategic
initiative so you have somebody like the
see a CIO say you know within IT you
know from now on I want to establish
scrum and so you have executive
management level support and you get in
consultants you hire consultants to come
in and help to train people and help to
run scrum projects and then that will be
then top-down rather than a bottom-up
approach however you approach it I would
really recommend that you first run the
series of scrum pilots pilot projects
where you buy your experiment with scrum
where you find the best way to to
leverage scrum but also employ scrum
properly within the organization before
you attempt any form of rollout and you
know your organization wise rollout of
scrum so basically a piecemeal growth
approaches is I think what works best
for generations and you know not to
discourage you but but just as a as a as
a piece of advice I guess scrum doesn't
reduce deep change into organizations
and it does challenge conventional ways
of thinking and in acting so it does
challenge conventional work habits so
you know introducing scrum particularly
in large organizations and organizations
whose company
which is not in line not very much in
line with with the agile values means
that there will be a certain amount of
impediments that surface table there may
also be a certain amount of friction
that is likely to happen and you know
it's probably just a good idea to be
aware of it and and you know it to be
prepared to a certain extent but you'll
never find out these things until you
try it so the best thing you can do is
really try it you know see how it works
for you see what issues you run in to
see what benefits you can you can reap
and take things from there ok so last
question for me a question I always ask
at this point when shouldn't I do scrum
are there are any things I do mention
already with the the culture or the
company doesn't fit very well to the
culture of scrum anything else comes to
mind there well I'd say they're really
two situations I can think of when you
shouldn't do scrum one is when the
company is doing really well so you know
your value creation is great your
profits are developing really nicely
your employees are very happy and your
customers are highly satisfied I mean if
you're in that situation why should you
change why should you introduce scrum I
mean you must be doing something that is
very similar to to agile or lean or
scrum in one way or the other so you
know I mean that's that's perfect that's
brilliant congratulations but the second
scenario I can think of when I wouldn't
recommend that you try to introduce
scrum is when you know from your own
recent and personal experience that
management is not willing to change or
embrace change that management is not
willing to empower teams and allow teams
then against some level of decision
making to the teams and that management
holds onto to dysfunctional command and
control habits if that's the case then
I'd recommend that you resign
immediately and look for any an employer
that truly respects its employees I mean
you know a situation like this you know
I find it in a situation like this I
find it really difficult to imagine how
you can successfully establish scrum I
mean scrum is is likely to bring about
some form of
of deeply change possibly some form of
culture change in your organization and
how easy that is
for for your organization and for your
teams you never thought find out until
you try okay anything else you want to
add on on the topic I think scrum is fun
I think most most teams that employ
scrum enjoyed very much enjoy very much
the way of working together the close
collaboration there some people have
struggled with it but generally speaking
most of the teams I've worked with have
have really strived have really excelled
using scrum and most of the product
owners I've met have been very pleased
have been delighted with the results the
teams could could accomplish so I think
it's definitely worth trying out scrum
giving it a go if you need any form of
support the scrum Alliance websites is
probably a good place to look for
further information supports training if
you want to if you feel you have any
training needs so that's probably a good
good place to go and visit ok thanks for
your time and was a great interview
thank you very much my pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details